- Opportunities to use AI
for smarter human resource management
exist in all aspects of the HR value chain,
job search platforms, candidate screening,
training and development,
promotion decisions,
even dismissal.
Like every technology,
AI can also be misused or abused.
People may put up with perceived unfairness
in many context
but if it's their livelihood,
and sense of self-worth
perceived unfairness can easily lead
to tearing the company in the media, lawsuits,
or even violence.
Companies need to be particularly conscious
about using AI for HR in ethical,
and bias-free ways.
Let's start with the use of AI
by job search platforms such as LinkedIn,
and ZipRecruiter.
These platforms recommend open positions
to individuals and candidates to companies.
Nearly always,
the platform needs to use natural
language processing to decode,
and individuals credentials on the one hand,
and job requirements on the other.
Consider now the use of AI to screen candidates.
Most large employers ask people to apply online.
They input always includes resume information
but may also include
asynchronous video interviews.
Companies can also look at the candidates
social media posts and government databases
such as police records.
AI models play a crucial role
in screening this information.
Natural language processing technology
is essential to decode the candidate's
application as well as text-based
social media postings.
In turn,
computer vision technology is essential
to interpret video interviews
as well as images and video post on social media.
There are no ethical issues with using AI
to decode the candidate's application,
and to assess fit with the company's needs.
It's also reasonable
for companies to analyze government databases
to assess risks of criminality or terrorism.
However, I contend that it is bad practice
to use AI to assess someone's personality
from video interviews.
Personality is a complex construct.
Today's AI is too rudimentary to decode it
from video interviews,
and most experts view it as no better
than trying to extract oil from a snake.
Regarding analysis of social media posts,
it's a gray area.
These posts exist in the public domain,
and the content can be analyzed well
to assess someone's interests and views,
though not their personality.
The issue is privacy.
Also some governments require
that asked by candidate,
the company must be able to explain
specifically why he or she was rejected.
AI is mostly a black box.
And saying that my AI did it,
would not be an acceptable answer
to these governments.
How about using AI for training and development?
Translation systems developed using AI
are already very competent across many languages.
Companies can use these systems
to translate their online training material
into multiple languages quickly,
and inexpensively.
AI tools can also be used
to assess an individual's grasp
of specific materials accurately,
and to suggest the next module in the program.
As a result,
people can learn in a more personalized manner.
Finally, let's look at how AI is used
to decide who to promote.
As with screening job applicants,
this context also has potential for misuse of AI.
Documented cases exist of companies
or consultants training AI models
on historical data pertaining
to who was promoted in the past or not.
In the US,
such an approach is likely to yield AI models
that may disproportionately favor white males
even when others are more qualifying.
It is an imperative that companies be especially
vigilant when using AI to guide them
in making promotion decisions.
Building on these ideas,
I propose the following assignment.
Pick three different HR processes
in your company.
How might you deploy AI to manage these processes
more intelligently?