- AI can drive product innovation
in one or both of two ways.
As an embedded feature of the end product,
or as a tool to design and develop the end product.
I use the generic term product to refer
to both products and services.
Let's look at AI as an embedded feature of the end product.
The starting point must always be to gain insights
into your customer's known as well as hidden needs.
Doing so often requires immersion in the customer's world,
as well as understanding the needs of their customers.
Deep insights will almost always reveal
that some needs are being met at best partially,
and some not at all.
The next step is to explore how one or more AI tools,
computer vision, natural language processing,
complex computational capability, or robotics,
can be embedded in the product
to meet these needs more completely.
As an example, take John Deere's See & Spray tractors.
In recent years, environmental sustainability
has become a growing imperative for farmers.
Meeting this goal requires that farmers
cut down on the use of chemicals.
As the world's leading agricultural machinery company,
John Deere has stepped in to help find a solution.
The company's answer, embed computer vision
in an attachment to its tractors.
As the tractor moves through a farm,
an array of high-resolution cameras
takes images of whatever is growing underneath.
An untrained human eye would have a tough time
distinguishing between a crop and a weed.
However, a neural network trained through a million images,
a case of supervised learning, is able to classify
a weed from a crop, almost flawlessly.
The AI then directs automated nozzles to spray herbicides
on just the weeds.
The end result for the farmer,
80% reduction in the use of herbicides
as well as significant cost savings.
Let's now look at AI as a tool for product development.
By way of example, consider the challenge
of developing small organic molecules.
Organic chemists have historically relied
on intuition to figure out
how to synthesize a desired molecule.
The number of possible options,
most of which are dead ends, is simply too large
to use pure logic to find the right answer.
Marwin Segler, a German organic chemist come AI researcher,
decided to tackle this challenge differently.
Segler fed the AI system almost all of the known
single-step organic chemistry reactions,
about 12.4 million in total.
He specified the end goal,
a specific desired organic molecule.
A reinforcement learning algorithm then got to work,
using a neural network to discover a multi-step
synthesis route and the required starting reagents.
The benefits, speed, efficiency, and cost savings.
Interestingly, now that Segler has demonstrated
what AI can do, it has become possible for chemists
to invent new drug molecules
not previously thought possible.
The opportunities to use the AI as a tool
for accelerating product innovation are universal.
They include making sense of unstructured data,
for gaining deep insights about customers' needs,
as well as exploring a much larger number
of possible designs to discover a short list
of the best options.
Now think of at least one innovation opportunity
of each type within your company.
How might you be able to embed
some type of AI in one of your products or services
to dramatically improve its functionality
for the customer, and how might you be able to use AI
as a tool to accelerate the next product development
or redevelopment initiative?