- Assume that you work for a nationwide
used vehicle retailer and want to train
an ML model to take the guesswork
out of estimating the market value of used cars.
How do you go about it?
As the first step,
you need to assemble a robust data set
containing relevant data on recent transactions
in several thousand used cars.
Let's say you have good data
on close to 10,000 cars.
For each transaction,
Your database should include data
on the output variable that is sales price
and a number of input features.
For each car, the features might include
make and model, launch year, mileage, color,
secondary options, such as type of seat,
entertainment system, et cetera,
exterior and interior condition,
repair history, accident history, and so forth.
You would then get the data cleaned up
and the various labels and formats
standardized across all transactions.
Since you already have an answer key
in your training data set,
that is, for each car,
values of input features and the resulting sales price.
It is clear that this context
requires a supervised learning algorithm.
It would generally be wise for you
to pick a few different but pertinent
supervised learning algorithms.
Train an ML model on each algorithm
and then pick the algorithm that beats others
in yielding the best model.
The next step is to specify
several hyper parameters for each algorithm.
These attributes that are specified ex ante
to guide the algorithm in carrying out the training task.
Some of the critical hyper parameters include
a measure of model performance,
also called the loss function.
That is how accurately the model estimates
sales prices when compared with actual sales prices.
How the data set should be split
between a training set, a validation set,
and a test set.
Training set refers to data used
for training the machine learning model.
Validation set refers to data
used for measuring the performance
of a trained model and to decide
how to fine tune the hyper parameters
before running the retraining again.
Finally, test set refers to data
used to measure and compare the accuracy
of the best trained ML model
yielded by each of the different algorithms.
The number of epochs, that is the number of times
you want the entire training set
to go through the ringer to improve the accuracy
of the ML model being trained
for that particular algorithm.
Within each epoch, there often will be a number
of iterations each using a smaller batch
from the larger training set.
Specify the number of iterations
and the batch size for each iteration.
The number of hidden layers in the neural network.
Hidden layers increase the model's ability
to look for complex interrelationships
among the various input features
that determine the output value.
It's the multiplicity of hidden layers
that differentiates deep neural networks
from shallow neural networks.
Once the hyper parameters are specified,
you let each algorithm train its ML model.
After each round of training,
you would use the validation data
to measure the accuracy of the model
and then fine tune the hyper parameters,
redo the training, measure the accuracy again,
and repeat the process until you feel
that you have the best possible model for this algorithm.
You should thus end up with the best trained ML model
from each of the different algorithms.
You would then assess and compare
the performance of these best models
using the test set.
After this, you would know which is the best
of the best model and thus, the best algorithm.
The final step is to decide
whether even the best ML model is good enough
when compared with human judgment.
If it's better, you may make this
your primary valuation tool.
If it's good enough, but not better,
you may use it to augment human judgment.
But if it's much worse, you may shelve it
until better data or better algorithms become available.