- Doing business without market research
is akin to flying an airplane blind.
While casual market research is as old
as human civilization,
systematic market research began in the 1920s
and is now a well-developed discipline.
Now withstanding developments
over the last hundred years,
market research is in the early stages
of a profound AI-powered revolution.
Market research practitioners are reexamining
every aspect of how AI can help discover better answers
to marketing questions, such as:
What do your target customers
and consumers want and need, and why?
What are they willing to pay, and why?
What do they expect from your products and service?
How do they perceive what you offer?
What's your brand awareness and brand image?
Who are your competitors?
Their strengths and weaknesses?
How are these changing?
AI's biggest impact lies in using the power
of natural language processing
and computer vision to tap into unstructured data.
Doing so can broaden the external ecosystem
that can be tapped into
and deepen the insights gathered from doing so.
Let me highlight four of the most important ways
AI can help you tap into unstructured data
for market research.
First, AI can help marketers
capture the information embedded in social media posts,
on platforms such as LinkedIn,
Facebook, Twitter, TikTok, YouTube, and the like.
Worldwide, every single adult younger than 40
already spend more than two hours
on social media every single day.
Almost all social media posts exist in a form
of free-form text, audio, images, and video.
AI can decode this unstructured data
to yield better insights about the wants, needs,
attitudes, and behaviors of target consumers.
Second, AI can unlock insights buried
in contact center recordings.
Most companies use contact centers where customers can ask
about product, place orders, file complaints,
or seek product support.
Companies have long relied on contact center personnel
to log the call and record a few relevant details.
This practice leads to a vast under-utilization
of available information.
AI-powered tools for natural language understanding
can interpret and codify
all of these recordings far more efficiently
and in real time.
Third, AI can make focus groups more insightful.
Focus groups, whereby a moderator facilitates discussion
among a select group of six to 10 people
to discuss a topic in some depths,
are are a staple of market research.
Typically, companies rely on their observers
to make sense of the discussion.
The risk is that corporate personnel can be selective
in what they take in
and biased in interpreting what they do take in.
AI can potentially do a much better job
at interpreting all of the visual and audio data
without any bias.
Now, think about the next two market research studies
that your organization may need to launch.
How might you deploy AI tools to enrich
and deepen these studies?