- Artificial intelligence is transforming every function
in every industry, be it agriculture, banking,
healthcare, or transportation.
- Here are some of the key takeaways from this course
on artificial intelligence and business strategy.
- AI can be defined as any computer system that mimics
to at least some degree natural intelligence
exhibited by humans and other species.
- [Left Speaker] The three major approaches to developing AI
are supervised learning, unsupervised learning,
and reinforcement learning.
- Data to AI is like fuel to a fire.
The cleaner, richer, and larger the dataset
on which it is trained, the more accurate
your AI model will be.
- For market research, AI's biggest impact
lies in using the power of natural language processing
and computer vision to tap into unstructured data.
- AI can help hyper-segmentation strategies where each buyer
and each user could eventually become a segment of one.
- AI can drive product innovation
either as an embedded feature of the end product
or as a tool to design and develop the end product.
- Leading-edge companies are starting to build digital twins
of their supply chains, deploying AI to manage
the digital twins and using the output
to augment their decisions and actions.
- AI can be deployed for smarter management
of all aspects of the HR value chain: job search platforms,
candidate screening, training and development,
promotion decisions, even departures.
- Since we are all human, society seems willing
to accept human frailties much more readily
than errors attributable to machines.
This creates moral dilemmas regarding how to deploy AI
in contexts where it can affect life or death decisions.
- Since AI models are trained on historical data,
there is serious risk that deploying such a model
can perpetuate and even amplify past biases.
You can pursue systematic approaches
to mitigate these risks.
- Last but not least, AI will affect jobs in three ways.
It will augment and alter but not eliminate some jobs.
It will eliminate the need for some jobs.
And it will create entirely new jobs,
sometimes in entirely new industries
that did not exist before.
- We wish you success on the never-ending journey
of learning about and deploying AI.