- Three major elements
of any company's internal operations are designing
and building the factory or service center,
day-to-day operations and quality control.
Using concrete examples from BMW, DoorDash and Landing.AI,
let's look at how these companies are deploying AI
across the three domains.
BMW is partnering with NVIDIA
to use AI for designing a new drive trained factory.
The partners have deployed NVIDIA'S Omniverse software
to create a digital twin of the entire factory,
enabling managers to see in photorealistic detail
how the factory will look and operate.
The virtual factory shows all machine tools and workers
exactly where they will be stationed.
As virtual parts move through the virtual factory,
the software even takes into account
the effects of gravity, material type and workers tools.
While factory builders have used simulations for many years,
today's digital twins, like BMWs, are radically different
in terms of the number of factors they incorporate.
This richness of inputs enables engineers
to simulate the actual working of the factory
at a level much closer to reality.
And many of today's AI algorithms simply did not exist,
even 15 years back.
As these algorithms run through millions of cycles
to gather training data,
they help the engineers understand what's suboptimal
and how they might tweak the overall factory design.
DoorDash showcases the use of AI in day-to-day operations.
DoorDash is a logistics company
that enables customers to order and get goods delivered
from local merchants.
To use DoorDash to order from say a restaurant,
you log in and choose the restaurant.
Once you pick what you want, DoorDash shows you the bill
and the estimated delivery time.
You check out and wait.
How does DoorDash predict the delivery time?
The company uses a supervised learning algorithm
to train its ML model.
Historical training data include the actual delivery time,
as well as input details pertaining to each order,
the merchant, a timestamp, as well as details
pertaining to the neighborhood
such as number of outstanding orders,
number of available couriers, day of the week,
holiday or not, et cetera.
As new data emerges, the model gets retrained regularly.
The goal is to be accurate to the last minute.
Overshoot and customers may not order.
Undershoot and they may get angry.
Behind the scenes, AI also plays a role
in DoorDash's logistics engine,
balancing supply and demand of couriers,
planning optimal routes with changing traffic patterns
and matching couriers to merchants
and customers in real time,
picking the optimal solution from millions of combinations.
Finally, Landing.AI
illustrates the use of AI for quality control.
Founded by Stanford's professor Andrew Ng,
this company helps clients manage their internal operations.
One such client is a steel company
that must routinely test for defects in steel sheets.
Defects can be problematic
in terms of aesthetics, functionality or both.
However, this is not true of all defects.
So the key challenge is not merely to identify a defect
but to figure out which is problematic and which not.
For AI, this is a supervised learning problem.
To train the ML model,
Landing.AI has worked with human inspectors
to label each type of defect as problematic or not,
paying particular attention to accuracy and consistency
across different inspectors.
Once trained, the machine learning model has proved
to be more accurate than the human inspectors.
For a large steel mill, even 1% greater accuracy
pays off very quickly for the investment in AI.
Now, analyze all three aspects
of your companies internal operations.
Designing and building a new factory or service center,
day-to-day operations and quality control.
How might you apply AI
to improve upon what you currently do?