- Diversity is an innate feature
of all natural phenomena, including us humans.
We differ from each other by DNA, sex, race,
ethnicity, age, nationality,
socioeconomic status, family context, friendships,
life experiences, you name it.
For marketers, a direct implication of diversity
is that markets are segmented and that companies
should aim to develop tailored strategies
for different segments.
Marketers have long faced two major hurdles
in implementing good segmentation strategies.
One, lack of rich data on buyers.
Two, very high cost of customization.
Developments in information and production technologies
have enabled companies to overcome these hurdles
to some extent.
Today, the rise of AI is pushing the envelope much further
towards hyper-segmentation, whereby each buyer
and each user could eventually become a segment of one.
Let's see how.
The majority of adults now have an online presence.
While some data is private, much of it is public.
Also, companies always have data
on every customer they have interacted with.
Combining internal with external data
can give marketers far richer insights
into the peculiarities of every single buyer.
Unsupervised machine learning algorithms,
such as k-means clustering, can parse us through
this large, growing and constantly changing database
more precisely than traditional statistical measures.
This is how AI-savvy banks and insurers
can develop a finely tailored risk profile of each customer,
even in those cases where the customer may have
no credit history and no hard assets,
but does have a social media presence
and a network of contacts.
This analysis can enable the bank or the insurer
to offer interest rates or insurance premium
that are more precisely and more richly informed
than those from competitors.
AI can also help develop more finely-tailored
marketing campaigns, delivering the right message
to the right target audience
via the right channels at the right time.
Each time you search for something on Google or Amazon,
the company learns a bit more about what you want
right now in real time.
This data goes immediately to work,
sending you tailored messages that have proved effective
with people most similar to you
along a broad array of factors.
The likely outcome?
Lower cost of customer acquisition.
Marketers can also deploy AI's trial
and error learning approach.
Let's say the goal is to decode
what combination of headline, image, copy,
colors, and time of delivery of an ad
would be most effective for each viewer.
Based on past data, the algorithm could begin
by serving viewers different combinations
with a high probability of success.
It would then learn by looking at
who clicks on which combination.
Through further iterations,
it would have refined the segmentation
as well as become smarter at serving
even more customized messages and formats for each viewer.
The root cause behind much of the waste in marketing budgets
is knowing only partially or not at all
what products or service a potential customer
may be ready to buy,
or if they are already inclined to buy something,
how to upsell and what to cross-sell.
Deploying AI to generate deeper insights
into each unique buyer and buying context
can significantly increase the return
on marketing expenditures.
Building on these ideas,
you may like to pursue three questions.
First, what data about your actual and potential customers
do you already have within the company?
Second, what data exists externally,
but is currently untapped?
Third, how might AI be deployed to parse through this data
to enable better segmentation strategies for your company?