- Data to AI is like fuel to a fire.
The cleaner, richer and larger the dataset
on which it is trained the more accurate
your AI model will be.
Here are five of the most important steps
towards building a robust dataset.
First, strive for maximum consistency
in the labels attached to,
and the format of each case in your dataset.
Lack of standardization is like ambient noise
when you are trying to listen to someone in a room.
Take VideoHealth, a startup that uses AI
to help dentists diagnose teeth x-rays.
As noted in the Harvard case, video obtained
several million x-rays from dental service organizations
and used a subset of these to train the AI model.
They realized, however, that image formats
and clinical labeling conventions
varied widely across dental practices.
Video developers built software
to standardize image formats and labels.
This consistency was essential
for building a more accurate AI model.
Second, assess whether the dataset
is rich enough in terms of features,
that is variables associated with each case.
A richer set of relevant features
will create a more accurate AI model.
Say you want to build an AI model
to recommend what jacket might go well
with a pair of trousers that a female customer
is considering on your online store.
Some of the relevant features
might include her purchase history,
her age, her ethnicity, her profession, whether she lives
in a large city or a small town, even her climatic region.
If you do not have information on some of these features
your AI model will be less accurate than it could be.
Third, look for missing data.
One solution is to manually collected missing information.
With large datasets this can be time consuming
and expensive, an alternative can be
to fill in the missing values
via statistical interpolation from other cases.
Yet, another alternative can be to train the AI model only
on those features where you have more complete data,
or on features that are more important.
Fourth, assess the possibility
of unacceptable biases embedded in the database.
Say, you are an HR manager and want to train
an AI model to help screen job applicants.
In this case, you need to evaluate
whether ethnic or gender biases of your predecessors
may have made the database a poor predictor
of how future hiring decisions should be made.
Later, in this course, we discuss
some of the ways historical biases
can be accounted for when training an AI model.
Fifth, assess whether the size
of your database is large enough.
A few thousand cases may suffice when the connection
between inputs and outputs is simple.
For example, training an AI model
to identify the makes and models
of cars based on real view images.
However, if the number of relevant factors is larger
and the connections between inputs and outputs
more complex, for example, estimating the value
of a used car you'd need a much larger dataset.
Organizations with multiple units doing similar things
in different locations often fail
to centralize the collection of data.
This is a needlessly missed opportunity
to assemble a larger database.
Another important action is to standardize,
automate and centralize the collection
of data from every transaction.
Most importantly, organizations need proactive
operational protocols defining the what,
why, how, and who of data collection.
Now, consider two opportunities
in your organization to train and deploy AI models.
Analyze how you would construct
a robust data pipeline in each of these two contexts.