- I'd like to ask you a question.
Have you used AI in the last 24 hours?
If your answer is no,
let me ask you, if you have used face recognition
to unlock your smartphone
or interact with autocorrect or voice-to-text features?
If so, then you're already a regular AI user.
We may not realize it
but we are already surrounded by AI.
It's in our smartphones,
it's in YouTube's recommendation engine,
it's in Google Search.
It's in many of the driver assist features
in Tesla cars.
It's in many hospitals where AI is starting
to help radiologists diagnose MRI images.
It's in our policing systems
where facial recognition is used increasingly
to identify suspects.
So what exactly is artificial intelligence?
The key to answering this question lies
in first defining the term natural intelligence.
That is intelligence as exhibited by humans
and other artificial.
According to the American Psychological Association,
intelligence refers to the ability
to understand complex ideas,
to adapt effectively to the environment,
to learn from experience
and to engage in various forms of reasoning.
Using this definition as a starting point,
we can define AI as a computer system
that exhibits these traits
to at least some degree.
By this definition,
it's easy to conclude that a calculator
would not qualify as an example of artificial intelligence.
While it can do complex calculations,
it does not adapt to the environment
and it certainly does not learn from experience.
That said, not everybody in the AI community
dismisses the calculator as not being an example
of very rudimentary AI.
Nearly 400 years back
when the French mathematician Blaise Pascal
invented the first mechanical calculator,
many a journalist ascribed human-like intelligence
to this simple machine.
After all, what differentiated humans from animals
was that humans could calculate, animals couldn't.
So if a machine can calculate,
it must be called intelligent.
Looking back, if we now conclude
that no, a calculator is certainly not intelligent,
it's worth noting that we humans
have long suffered from hubris.
Once a machine starts doing cognitive tasks as well
or better than humans,
we have a tendency to denigrate it
as merely calculative ability
not worthy of being called intelligence.
Even today, a small minority of AI scientists
dismiss facial recognition,
natural language understanding,
and driver assist features as not really true AI.
To me, such values reflect,
mold the hubris of these scientists,
then how we should define AI.
As may be obvious by now,
AI is not a binary black-or-white concept.
That is a computer system is either AI or not AI.
Rather, like human IQ,
computer systems also vary
in their degree of intelligence.
Merely 15 years back,
the accuracy of image recognition systems
to classify photos that did or did not include the image
of a cat hovered around 50%.
No better than tossing a coin.
Today it's in the high 90s.
Similarly, almost by the day,
AI systems are getting smarter
at interpreting MRI scans,
understanding and generating speech
and autonomous navigation.
Perhaps in 10 years' time,
we would look back and wonder
why we ever called present-era systems as AI,
similar to how we view calculators today.
Present-day AI systems are extremely domain specific.
An AI that is good at facial recognition
is useless at understanding speech and vice versa.
Domain specificity also implies
that some types of AI are already far smarter
than humans could ever be.
For example, playing chess or the Chinese game of Go.
On the other hand, in most other domains,
humans remain much more intelligent than computer systems.
The biggest difference currently
between human and artificial intelligence
is that human intelligence is multifaceted.
The same brain can read, write, speak,
calculate, interpret emotions
and do 1,000 other cognitive tasks effortlessly.
Even the best AI systems today
reflect narrow, artificial intelligence.
Now, think about the many aspects of your work context
that are already or could soon be powered by AI.