- Supply chains of tomorrow must be designed
to respond to much greater uncertainty
than was true even 10 years back.
The numerous factors buffeting supply chains
include pandemics, demand volatility,
raw material disruptions, labor shortages,
geopolitical tensions, cyber attacks, terrorism
and more frequent extreme weather patterns.
As a result, in designing and managing supply chains,
the ability to recover quickly
from unexpected developments
has become as important as maximizing efficiency.
Every supply chain is a network of organizations.
Think about raw material mines, factories,
trucks, ships, trains, ports, warehouses.
All parts of a complex network.
How does one ensure that such a network
can be not only efficient
but also resilience and responsive?
The answer lies in ensuring
that the network exhibits the following properties.
One, end-to-end visibility.
Like control towers,
network managers must maximize visibility
into every node and every link,
as well as the external factors
that may cause turbulence
in these nodes and links.
Visibility helps ensure that unexpected changes anywhere
in the system get anticipated, recognized,
and if needed, acted upon with minimum delay.
Two, agility.
When unexpected changes do occur,
network managers must be able
to figure out the best response
and act on it rapidly.
To create such a network,
leading edges companies are starting
to build digital twins of their supply networks,
deploying AI to manage the digital twins
and using the output to augment their decisions and actions.
A digital twin refers to a simulation
of the physical network in a computer,
creating a replica that mirrors real-world objects
and the links between them.
The digital twin integrates
the company's internal private data,
including LT sensors with external public data,
such as satellite images,
weather predictions and political developments.
Let's say you have a supplier in Wenzhou, China.
The digital twin can automatically incorporate the risk
of an incoming hurricane,
something that will be hard of people to do
when dealing with dozens or even hundreds
of nodes and links.
In this manner, a digital twin can anticipate problems
before that happen.
It can also use AI to recommend
or even execute the optimal solution.
While simulating reality is not a new idea,
the value of AI models lies in their ability
to decipher nonlinear interactions
among very large
and constantly changing sets of data,
both structured and unstructured.
Similar to interactive games,
such as chess and Go,
reinforcement learning algorithms
train company-specific AI models
by playing millions of what-if games
on the multidimensional board of a digital twin.
Once the model has mastered
a particular supply chain network,
it springs into action when needed.
Let's say there's an accident
at a parts supplier in Malaysia.
The AI would not only alert you
but also suggest actions,
such as placing an immediate order
with a distributor in California
who happens to have inventory in stock.
AI models can deal with such complexity far better
than even the smartest supply chain managers.
They also keep retraining constantly.
Companies such as Amazon
have been using the digital twin concept
to manage their supply chains for some time.
Now tech providers, such as Google and NVIDIA
have started offering these capabilities to other companies.
Building on these ideas,
you may want to analyze your company's supply chain as well.
Who should be the members of a team
to assess how to build a digital twin
for your supply chain?
How many tiers upstream could you go
in building an excellent mirror of the physical reality?