- When AI models are trained on historical data,
containing answer keys,
there is serious risk
that deploying such a model
can perpetrate and even amplify past biases.
This is not an issue if the AI model is being trained
to recognize cats in pictures
or detect cancer in MRI scans.
However, if the model is being trained
to screen job applicants,
assess mortgage applicants
or decide who to release on parole,
AI models can suffer from embedded historical biases.
To illustrate, an August 2021 study found
that in the US, lenders using AI models
were 80% more likely to reject Black applicants
than similar White applicants.
Engineers training AI models
and people from the business side working with them
can adopt a number of measures
to reduce the risk of perpetuating historical biases.
I illustrate some of these here.
First, look at the dataset
to be used for training an AI model.
If it contains too few cases of a population segment,
the model's overall accuracy can be high,
even though its accuracy
for the particular population segment
is extremely low.
This is why face recognition systems in the US
have tended to perform poorly
with Black faces, especially those of Black women.
Since most developers are White or Asian males,
they have tended to be oblivious
to the potential for such bias.
Imagine the risk faced by Black people
when stopped by police who use such systems
to check their faces against those
of suspected criminals.
The way to counter such risk
is to assemble the dataset in such a way
that it contains large numbers
of cases for every relevant population segment,
especially those at possible risk
of AI-driven biases.
Second, use technical fixes
to reduce bias in the AI models.
One such approach is adversarial de-biasing,
which uses one AI model to reduce bias in another.
Assume that race is the most likely bias-inducing attribute
an AI model recommends against a particular applicant.
The second AI model
would take the output of the first model
and try to guess based on all attributes other than race
the applicant's race.
If it can do so correctly,
more often than by chance,
then the first model would need
to be retuned and the process repeated
until the second model
can no longer identify the applicant's race.
Third, conduct fairness audits
before an AI model is released for general use.
There are multiple ways to do so.
One approach is to use two random subsets
of the historical data.
In one subset, mask all sensitive attributes,
for example, by coding every applicant as a white male.
If the AI model deals similar predictions
across the two data subsets,
then it can be deemed bias free.
Otherwise, you need back to square one measures
to mitigate bias.
At a broader organizational and societal level,
measures to reduce the risks
of algorithmic bias include a diverse AI talent pool
so that the developers are sensitive to the risks
of AI bias.
Mandatory AI ethics courses
in engineering and computer science programs.
And even regulatory actions by policymakers.
The European Union is one such government
actively contemplating regulatory actions,
especially in use contexts
where the harm caused by biased AI models
is likely to be high.
For your own organization,
I suggest two assignments.
First, take an existing AI model in use.
How would you conduct a fairness audit on this model?
Second, consider the most likely new deployment
of AI within the company.
How would you ensure
that the new AI model would be biased free?