- Google CEO, Sundar Pichai,
has termed artificial intelligence
as more profound than fire or electricity.
- NVIDIA's CEO, Jensen Quang,
calls AI the most powerful technology the world has known.
This is the age of AI.
- Artificial intelligence is a general purpose technology
that is becoming more powerful by the day
and being deployed in all walks of life and work.
Within the next five years, every job,
every function, and every industry
will be transformed by the power of AI.
Hi, I'm Anil Gupta, Michael Dingman Chair,
and Professor of Strategy at the Smith School of Business,
the University of Maryland at College Park.
- And I'm Haiyan Wang,
Managing Partner of the China India Institute.
- Join us at LinkedIn Learning,
where we start by clarifying what AI is
and how it is developed,
and then spend a good chunk of the time
examining how AI can be deployed
to create competitive advantages,
both on stage and backstage.
Join us on this exciting journey.