- The goal of developing an AI tool is
to build a machine learning, or ML, model
that can take an input such as a tooth x-ray
and deliver an output such as whether or not
there is a cavity.
Training any ML model starts with two inputs,
a machine learning algorithm, and a data set.
Think of the algorithm as a specialized computer program,
designed to help an ML model learn
to do a particular task intelligently.
At a macro level, there are three different types
of machine learning algorithms,
each relevant for certain types of tasks.
I use the word type to highlight
that there exist many different algorithms within each type.
Also ML engineers keep tweaking their algorithms regularly.
Supervised learning refers
to those machine learning algorithms
where the machine learns
from answer keys provided in the training data.
For example,
in developing an ML model
to classify incoming emails a spam, not spam,
each email in the training data set must have
a pre-specified label denoting whether it is spam or not.
As another example of supervised learning,
say you want to develop an ML model
to predict the sales impact of increased advertising
and our short term price discounts
for a perishable product such as packaged yogurt.
In this case
your training data set must include real information
on the sales impact
of previous advertising budgets and price changes.
Unsupervised learning refers
to those machine learning algorithms
that must train the ML model without having an answer key.
Instead, the model is trained
to identify patterns in available data.
Once the model has learned the patterns,
it applies this knowledge
to provide intelligent answers for new events.
As new data emerges, the ML model keeps refreshing itself.
Netflix's recommendation engine is a good example
of training via unsupervised learning.
Each time you open the Netflix app
the company's goal is
to present from top to bottom and from left to right
specific genres and movies that you may like to watch.
The faster you are able to locate a movie
that you would enjoy watching
the better it is for you and Netflix.
The algorithm builds the recommendation engine
by making use of everything in the database
about your historical viewing choices,
and mapping them against the choices made by other users
whose viewing habits very similar to yours.
Finally, reinforcement learning refers
to those machine learning algorithms
that must train an ML model
to make a sequence of interrelated decisions
where the quality
of any particular decisions rest fundamentally
on future decisions yet to be made.
For example, playing a game of chess
or driving a car autonomously.
From a decision making lens
such tasks are very different
from those which require only one short decisions
such as classifying an email a spam, not spam,
via supervised learning
or recommending a movie via unsupervised learning.
Think of an ML model that can play chess intelligently.
Whether it takes 20, 30, or 40 moves
to play a game of chess,
the only thing that matters is
whether you win or lose in the end,
the score is based on the joint effect of all moves,
and it is often impossible to know ex ante
whether any single move was a good or a bad one.
This is why training and AI to play chess requires
a reinforcement learning algorithm.
Now pick three or more opportunities in your company
where AI can be useful in helping to make better decisions.
Think about what type
of machine learning algorithm would be relevant
for each opportunity.