- We want you to visualize how AI
can create value for your company and your customers.
Let's look at some of the concrete ways
that Google, a company all of us interact with,
uses AI to create value for its customers.
Even among technology giants,
Google stands out as the leader,
both in developing the AI technology,
as well as deploying it
to power the diversity of its products and services.
Of the thousand different ways that Google deploys the AI,
from driverless cars to advertising to YouTube,
let me high three of their latest applications.
Let's start with search, Google's oldest service.
Google has long deployed AI
to make search more relevant to users.
Examples include Voice Search,
which enables users to pose queries via speech,
and RankBrain, which uses neural networks
to increase the relevance of search results.
The latest advance is MUM,
short form Multitask Unified Model,
which was showcased in mid-2021
and represents a step improvement.
MUM aims to integrate content and context
at a level not achieved so far.
Let's say you want to figure out
which school is best for your child.
The best answer would depend on deep knowledge
about your child, your family,
the school options available to you,
and the specific characteristics of each school.
In other word, the best answer requires
a deep integration of content and context.
Similar to this type of question,
MUM's mission is to help people meet
many of the fuzzy and complex information needs
in their daily lives.
The fewer the number of search queries
a user needs to make to come up with the best answer,
the better it is for him or her.
As another example, take Google's Pixel-branded smartphones.
In October, 2021, Google launched Pixel 6 and 6 Pro,
the latest models.
According to reviews,
these devices compete well
with the best from Apple and Samsung,
at significantly lower prices.
In some important ways,
they outdo them in terms of user benefits.
The differentiator in these smartphones
is the pervasive use of AI.
Pixel 6 runs on a custom-built tensor chip
designed to run multiple machine learning models
in the device itself instead of in the cloud.
As a result, everything in the device,
from audio quality to battery usage,
becomes smarter and the apps respond faster,
because information does not need to travel
back and forth between the device and the cloud.
A new Live Translate feature
enables the user to message back and forth
with real-life simultaneous translation
without opening a separate app.
And there is software that guides cameras
to determine the exposure and color balancing
much more accurately than any other device,
especially for people with darker skin,
a first ever feature in a smartphone.
Finally, look at Google's fora into drug discovery.
In late 2021, Google's parent, Alphabet,
launched a new company, Isomorphic Labs,
charged with using AI to discover new drugs,
Demis Hassabis, the Co-Founder and CEO of DeepMind,
a Google subsidiary and the company's spearhead
for AI research, will also serve as Isomorphic's CEO.
In addition to its own research,
Isomorphic will utilize DeepMind's AlphaFold technology,
which has already demonstrated the ability
to predict the structure of nearly every protein
in a human body with near perfect accuracy.
Isomorphic also announced
that while it will bring AI expertise to the table,
it will partner with pharma and biomedical companies
to assemble the complementary capabilities
needed to discover new treatments
and take them through clinical trials
and commercialization.
Now think about how you may be able to deploy AI
to make your products and services
more tailored to each customer's specific context,
to add new and better features to them,
and to develop entirely new products and services.