- While scientific efforts to mimic human intelligence
go back centuries,
the modern AI era began in the 1950s,
concurrent with the invention
of increasingly powerful digital computers.
A 1956 workshop at Dartmouth College
is widely regarded as the seminal event
that launched systematic research in AI.
In the first few decades.
Symbolic AI served as the dominant paradigm in AI.
The thinking was that computers can be made intelligent
by first decoding the facts
and decision rules that experts,
such as doctors used to undertake cognitive tasks
and then codifying this knowledge
into computer programs.
Symbolic AI exhibited early promise
with small demonstration programs.
The heightened expectations led to the rise
of so-called expert systems
in the late 1970s and 1980s.
Reality, however, proved to fall dramatically short
of the high hopes.
The fundamental problem with symbolic AI
was that experts could verbalize only a small fraction
of the knowledge in their brains.
As a result, this type of AI
could never be as smart as the experts, let alone smarter.
The real breakthrough in AI
and its exploding application
in all walks of life came about in the early 2010s.
This is when a new band of researchers
were able to utilize the explosion in cheap computing power
and the vast availability of internet-fed data
to implement their ideas
regarding deep neural networks.
This new paradigm differed radically from symbolic AI.
Unlike symbolic AI's top-down approach,
the neural network approach aimed
to make computers intelligent
by mimicking how babies learn.
They see adults walking and want to emulate them.
They try something and fall down.
They try again, perhaps a little differently.
After many tries, they learn to fall less often.
Further trial-and-error learning
eventually makes them experts at walking and running.
Could computers learn in a similar way?
The neural network paradigm
has proved to be hugely successful,
so much so that people such as Bill Gates
and Elon Musk have voiced alarm
at the risks of super intelligent AI
one day making humans expendable.
While super intelligent AI
is probably many years away,
it's worth looking at some of the questions
that AI researchers are working on today.
Few, short learning.
How to train an AI on small, rather than big data?
Transfer of learning.
How to enable an AI trained in one domain
to carry over the learning to another domain?
Accelerated learning.
How to dramatically accelerate learning by an AI.
For example, by creating its own synthetic data
or by having a master AI and a student AI work in tandem.
Explainable AI.
How can we go inside the black box
to understand the logic developed by an AI?
Generative AI.
How to develop an AI
that can generate truly novel output.
Multimodality.
How to enable an AI to take a diversity of data
such as audio, video, touch, et cetera,
simultaneously and come up
with integrated learning?
Human-computer interaction.
How to create robots
that can navigate a room full of people
and understand what is going on and be of assistance.
Merging of the human brain with AI.
How to enable the human brain
to communicate with the external world
without any hardware connection at all?
Neuralink, one of Elon Musk's companies,
is working on exactly this challenge.
Once you solve this problem,
a logical next step would be to merge human intelligence
with artificial intelligence.
Scary but also exciting.
It appears likely that many, if not all
of these questions will get answered within this decade.
While you may not have all the answers,
it would be useful to speculate how AI
will affect the way tasks you're responsible for
might be done differently five years from now
and 10 years from now.